I’m often asked
what my opinion
about a diet
or disease is.
Who cares what my or
anyone else’s opinion is.
All we should care about
is what the science says.
What does the best available
balance of evidence
Published in the peer-
reviewed medical literature
have to say right now?
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
There has been a
history of enthusiasm
for protein in the
nutrition world.
In fact, a century ago the
protein recommendations
were more than twice
what they are today.
Let’s start with a
public health case
for modernizing the definition
of protein quality.
In 2019, Dr. David Katz
and colleagues—
including one of my favorite
researchers, David Jenkins—
published a public health
case for modernizing
the definition of protein quality.
The prevailing definition seems to
have more to do with biochemistry
than the net effects on human health.
The popular concept that protein
is good, and the more the better,
coupled with a protein quality
definition that favors animal protein,
fosters the impression that eating
more meat, eggs, and dairy
is desirable and preferable,
but this is directly opposed
to nutrition guidelines that are
instead trying to push more plants.
Although protein malnutrition is still
prevalent in many areas of the world,
it is exceedingly rare
in the industrialized world,
where the most formidable
public health threat
is not something like kwashiorkor—
protein/calorie malnutrition—
but from chronic diseases.
In 2016, a landmark study
was published out of Harvard,
involving more than 100,000 people,
that found that replacing animal protein
with plant protein was associated
with lower risk of dying prematurely.
The worst seemed to be
processed meat like bacon,
as well as egg protein,
the egg whites,
but swapping in even just 3% plant
protein for any of the animal proteins—
processed meat, unprocessed meat,
chicken, fish, eggs, or dairy—
was associated with a
significantly lower risk
of arguably the most important
endpoint of all: death.
Yeah, but how do we
know it's the protein?
The researchers adjusted for factors
such as saturated fat intake,
which suggested it wasn't
just the animal fat.
Okay, but how does your body
even know the difference
between protein from a plant
and protein from an animal?
Isn't protein, protein?
No. Unlike animal protein,
plant protein is generally low
in branched-chain
amino acids, for example,
and decreased consumption
of branched-chain amino acids
improves metabolic health.
It could be the IGF-1,
a cancer-promoting growth
hormone that is boosted
by so-called high-quality
animal protein intake, though.
We suspect the IGF-1
connection is cause and effect,
since people who are born
to have higher IGF-1 levels
regardless of what they eat
do appear to suffer
higher rates of killers like
type 2 diabetes and heart disease.
Or it could be something the
Harvard researchers didn't control for
such as toxic pollutants like
as dioxins and PBCs,
since they tend to accumulate
up the food chain in cattle,
pigs, chickens, and fish,
and therefore end up on our plates.
So plant-based protein also
stands as an important step
to lower the body burden
of harmful pollutants.
If you don't think 100,000
people are enough,
how about 400,000 people?
The NIH-AARP study is the largest
diet cohort study in history.
And again, simply swapping
3% of calories from various
animal protein sources
with plant protein
was associated with 10%
decreased overall mortality,
and you get even twice that benefit
if you get rid of eggs, too.
That's not a surprise, since
egg consumption is associated
with a higher risk of developing
cardiovascular disease.
Put all the studies together on
dietary protein intake and mortality,
and people who eat more protein
tend to live shorter lives,
but this is mainly driven by the
harmful association of animal protein.
Plant protein intake is inversely
associated with mortality,
meaning those who eat more plant
protein tend to live longer lives.
More animal protein
may mean more mortality,
whereas more plant protein
is correlated with less mortality.
So the best of both worlds
would be to increase
the intake of plant protein
in place of animal protein.
In other words, as another
2020 meta-analysis concluded,
"Persons should be encouraged to
increase their plant protein intake
to potentially decrease
their risk of death."
Do vegetarians and vegans
get enough protein?
Let's find out.
The largest study in history
of those eating plant-based diets
recently compared the nutrient profiles
of about 30,000 non-vegetarians
to 20,000 vegetarians and
about 5,000 vegans, flexitarians,
and no meat except fish-eaters,
allowing us to finally put
to rest the perennial question,
“Do vegetarians get enough protein?”
The average requirement is
42 grams of protein a day.
Non-vegetarians get way more than
they need, and so does everyone else.
On average, vegetarians and vegans get
70% more protein than they need every day.
Surprising that there’s so much fuss
about protein in this country
when less than 3% of adults
don’t make the cut,
presumably folks on extreme calorie-restricted
diets who just aren’t eating enough food, period.
But 97% of Americans get enough protein.
There is a nutrient, though, for
which 97% of Americans are deficient.
Now that’s a problem nutrient.
That’s something we
really have to work on.
Less than 3% of Americans get even the
recommended minimum adequate intake of…
FIBER
So the question isn’t
“where do you get your protein?”
but “where do you get your fiber?”
We only get about 15 grams a day.
The minimum daily requirement is 31.5
so we get less than
half the minimum.
If you break it down
by age and gender,
after studying the diets
of 12,761 Americans,
the percent of men
between ages 14 and 50
getting the minimum
adequate intake? Zero.
This deficit is stunning in that dietary
fiber has been protectively associated
with the risk of diabetes,
metabolic syndrome,
cardiovascular disease, obesity,
and various cancers,
as well high cholesterol, blood
pressure, and blood sugars.
Therefore, it is not surprising
that fiber is now listed
as a nutrient of concern in the dietary
guidelines. Protein is not.
One problem is that most people have
no idea what’s in their food.
More than half of Americans think
steak is a significant fiber source.
By definition, fiber is only found in plants.
There is no fiber in meat, dairy or eggs,
and little or no fiber in junk food.
Therein lies the problem.
Americans should be eating more beans,
vegetables, fruits, whole grains.
How are we doing on that?
Well, 96% of Americans don’t eat the
recommended minimum daily intake of beans,
96% don’t eat the measly minimum for greens,
99% don’t get enough whole grains.
Look at these numbers.
Nearly the entire U.S. population fails
to eat enough whole plant foods.
And it’s not getting better, a lack
of progress that’s disappointing.
Even semi-vegetarians, though,
make the minimum for fiber.
And those eating completely plant-based
diets triple the average American intake.
Now when closing the fiber gap,
you’ll want to do it gradually,
no more than about five extra
grams of fiber a day each week
until you can kind of work your way up.
But it’s worth it.
Plant-derived diets tend
to contribute significantly
less fat, saturated fat, cholesterol,
and foodborne pathogens,
while at the same time offering more fiber,
folate, vitamin C, and phytochemicals,
all essential factors for disease prevention,
and optimal health and well being.
And the more plant foods, the better–
whole plant foods, the better.
If you compare the nutritional quality
of vegan versus vegetarian,
semi-vegetarian, pesco-vegetarian
and omnivorous diets,
traditional healthy diet indexing systems,
like compliance with
the dietary guidelines,
consistently indicate the most plant-based
diet as the most healthy one.
Finally today, we
examine the myth
that plant proteins
are incomplete.
All nutrients come from
the sun or the soil.
Vitamin D, the "sunshine vitamin," is created
when skin is exposed to sunlight.
Everything else comes
from the ground.
Minerals originate from the earth,
and vitamins from the plants and
micro-organisms that grow from it.
The calcium in a cow's milk
(and her 200-pound skeleton)
came from all the plants she ate,
which drew it up from the soil.
We can cut out the middle-moo, though,
and get calcium from the plants directly.
Where do you get
your protein?
Protein contains essential amino acids,
meaning our bodies can't make them
and so are essential to get from our diet.
But other animals
don't make them either.
All essential amino acids originate
from plants (and microbes),
and all plant proteins have
all essential amino acids.
The only truly "incomplete" protein
in the food supply is gelatin,
which is missing the amino
acid tryptophan.
So the only protein source that
you couldn't live on is Jell-O.
As I covered previously, those
eating plant-based diets
average about twice the average
daily requirement for protein.
Those who don't know where to get
protein on a plant-based diet
don't know beans!
Get it?
That's protein quantity, though.
What about protein quality?
The concept that plant protein was
inferior to animal protein
arose from studies performed on
rodents more than a century ago.
Scientists found that infant rats
don't grow as well on plants.
But infant rats don't grow as well
on human breast milk either,
so does that mean we shouldn't
breastfeed our babies?
Ridiculous! They're rats.
Rat milk has ten times more
protein than human milk,
because rats grow about ten times
faster than human infants.
It's true that some plant
proteins are relatively low
in certain essential amino acids.
So about 40 years ago, the myth of
"protein combining" came into vogue—
literally: the February '75 issue
of Vogue magazine.
The concept was that we needed to eat
"complementary proteins" together,
for example rice and beans,
to make up for their relative shortfalls.
This fallacy was refuted decades ago,
the myth that plant proteins are incomplete,
that plant proteins aren't as good,
that one has to combine proteins at meals.
These have all been dismissed by
the nutrition community as myths
decades ago, but many in medicine
evidently didn't get the memo.
Dr. John McDougall called out
the American Heart Association
for a 2001 publication that questioned
the completeness of plant proteins.
Thankfully though they've changed
and acknowledged now
that plant proteins can provide
all the essential amino acids;
no need to combine
complementary proteins.
It turns out our body
is not stupid.
It maintains pools of free
amino acids that can be used
to do all the complementing for us,
not to mention the massive protein
recycling program our body has.
Some 90 grams of protein is dumped
into the digestive tract every day
from our own body to get broken
back down and reassembled,
so our body can mix and match amino
acids to whatever proportions we need,
whatever we eat, making it practically
impossible to even design a diet
of whole plant foods that's sufficient
in calories, but deficient in protein.
Thus, plant-based consumers do not need
to be AT ALL concerned about amino acid
imbalances from the plant proteins
that make up our usual diets.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite to each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.